Register of the Vakhan Fomich Totomiants Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Vakhan Fomich Totomiants papers
1923-1951
2001C17
Hoover Institution Archives
1 microfilm reel (0.15 linear feet)
Writings and biographical data, relating to economic cooperative movements and theory, and to Russian émigré affairs.
Totomiants, Vakhan F. (Vakhan Fomich), b. 1875
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2001.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
Vakhan Fomich Totomiants was born into an Armenian family in Astrakhan' on 3 February 1875. He graduated from the University of Brussels (1898) and received his Ph. D. from the University of Kiev (1915). As a specialist in cooperative economics, he wrote several treatises on cooperatives and economics in general: Teoriia kooperatsii (1918), Istoriia ekonomicheskikh i sotsial'nykh uchenii (1921), Osnovy kooperatsii (1923), and Iz istorii russkoi ekonomicheskoi mysli (1956).
Generally considered to be one of the leading figures in the field, he taught in Kharkov', Kiev, Moscow and St. Petersburg, and following his emigration from Russia at several universities and institutes in Germany, Czechoslovakia and Bulgaria between the wars.
Chronology
1875 February 3 Born, Astrakhan', Russia
1898 Ph.D., University of Brussels, Belgium
1915 Ph.D., Kiev University
1918 Author, Teoriia kooperatsii
1921 Author, Istoriia ekonomicheskikh i sotsial'nykh uchenii
1922-1930 Taught at several universities and institutes in Prague, Czechoslovakia
1923 Author, Osnovy kooperatsii
1943 Author, Iz moikh vospominanii
1956 Author, Iz istorii russkoi ekonomicheskoi mysli
Scope and Content Note
Vakhan F. Totomiants was a prominent theorist of economic cooperation, with many published works on the subject to his credit. This collection contains a number of his newspaper articles, reviews of his works and unpublished writings, particularly on economic subjects.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Cooperative societies.; Russians--Czechoslovakia.
- Biographical File, 1928-1950 and undated (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Bibliography, biographical note and clippings, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Writings, 1923-1951 (Box 1)
  Books, articles and reviews, arranged chronologically by title
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1928-1950 and undated (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Folder 1: 1)
  - Biographical note (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings about or mentioning Totomiants (Folder 1: 3)
- WRITINGS, 1923-1951
  - General. (Folder 1: 4)
    Reviews of Totomiants' works in the German press, 1923-1928
  - "Cooperation,", n.d. (Folder 1: 5)
    Typescript
  - "The Co-Operative Anthology,", n.d. (Folder 1: 6)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Istoriia ekonomicheskikh i sotsial'nykh uchenii,", n.d. (Folder 1: 7)
  - "Iz moikh kooperativnykh vospominanii," Russkaia zhizn', n.d. (Folder 1: 8)
    Printed copy
  - "Kommunisticheskie i kooperativnye kolonii," Delo Truda-Probuzhdenie, n.d. (Folder 1: 9)
  - "Kratkii uchebnik po kooperatsii,", n.d. (Folder 1: 10)
  - "Rol' armian v tsivilizatsii,", n.d. (Folder 1: 11)
  - "Russkaia i armianskaia emigratsiia i kooperatsiia," Novaia zaria, n.d. (Folder 1: 12)
  - "Sozdanie sel'skoi tsivilizatsii," translation into Russian of a speech by George Russell before an agricultural cooperative society in Ireland (Folder 1: 13)
  - W. King, 1931 (Folder 1: 14)
  - : Kooperatsiia i 5 liet sushchestvovaniia v Sofii Russkago Kooperativnago Banka "ROTS,"., 1941 (Folder 1: 15)
    Printed copy. Includes two articles by Totomiants
  - Iz moikh vospominanii, 1943 (Folder 1: 16)
    Printed copy and review
  - "Rol' armian v kul'ture chelovechestva," Novaia zaria, 1951 June 9 (Folder 1: 17)